hello I'm your host David Barnard and
with me today Revenue cat CEO Jacob
eiding Our Guest today is Eric Crowley a
tech investment banker with GP bullhound
where he provides transaction advice and
capital to top companies in the consumer
subscription software space on the
podcast we talk with Eric about the B2B
opportunities for b2c apps the App Store
alone being bigger than most Fortune 500
companies in which current or future
company will build the Berkshire
Hathaway of consumer subscriptions
hey Eric thanks so much for joining us
on the podcast today thanks David Jacob
always nice to have you joining us as
well I'm great somebody told me I was
gonna have a call with a banker today
and I got super excited so it's great to
have you back Eric for number four for
Pete I think our first ever quite the
honor not just any Banker the consent I
said my favorite prescription software
Banker
my favorite Banker as well so Eric you
put out this report every year and the
reason you've been on four times is
because Jacob and I are continually
Blown Away by stuff you share in the
report and we're excited to have read
your very first one when we were both
super bullish on subscription apps and
not that many other people were but it
feels like every year you share
something that still blows my mind even
though I do this day in day out and this
year it's the fact that Apple's app
store is already by gross revenue bigger
than 450 out of the 500 Fortune 500
companies which I should know these
things right I look at these numbers
every day
but golly it's just huge and we don't
think about it in those terms yeah I
think it's something interesting because
a lot of people when they think consumer
subscription software they're oh it's a
cool initial industry and then you step
back and say okay well what is it part
of where's the storefront and so we just
did some research and this is all
publicly available information right you
go to the apple 10ks and 10qs read about
there's some really good research out
there but so when you start stacking up
the revenue it just grows consistently
year over year I think they're talking
about 95 billion this year wow okay like
how do you put such a large number of
comparison Tesla which is a phenomenal
company will do about 100 billion this
year Procter Gamble which every single
one of us owns something from them in
our bathroom for sure and probably our
kitchen they'll probably do 85 billion
gross not talking about profits even
yeah top line revenue and profit I think
this app store is phenomenally
profitable they don't break it up
specifically but rumors have 20 to 30
percent profit levels and so you're
talking about a 20 to 30 billion dollars
in profit and that'll rank them
extremely high within the space and so I
can't imagine shampoo is doing quite
those numbers yeah I mean it's all you
shampoo deodorant toothpaste you get a
whole bunch of services so then we okay
that's huge dollars okay and what's
included in there and there's a bunch
right just to be clear it's not just
consumer subscription there's some
gaming there's movies there's Apple TV
Apple music but all those things are
purchased through the Apple ecosystem
slash phones primarily the key thing we
like to talk about is it just shows you
know that business was probably doing
about 46 billion in 2019 and now it's
close to 100 right so that's almost a
doubling of content being purchased
through the App Store regardless of of
what type it is and it just shows that
this ecosystem there's argument around
consumer fatigue there's argument around
like how much more stuff could people
truly buy and the answer is a lot we
don't see that slowing down and then the
thing we really found fascinating was
that if you look at all the other
businesses out there that are
marketplaces within the App Store I mean
you kind of include both Google and
apple there's close to 6 million
applications these are small businesses
or large businesses running within that
ecosystem and so that's quite powerful
and I think even within our little niche
where you guys are playing right and
this is why I love Revenue cat which you
guys are building is there's close to a
billion subscriptions coming through the
app store today and many people have
multiple and so that number we expect is
just going to continue to grow it's
quite big when you start stacking it up
compared to other big Industries I was
talking to somebody about this this
weekend I don't believe there's a
natural limit on the depth of software
if that sounds a little heady but the
potential combinations of software are
essentially infinite and I think one of
the charts in the report also just shows
iPhone penetration like how many iPhones
are there which is over doubled in the
time since we started Revenue cat in
2017 which you look at the 20 year over
year you're like oh that's numbers but
not crazy but you compound that out for
not that long five years is not that
long and now we've suddenly there's two
iPhones for every one that there was
five years ago and as that continues to
expand you just have this fractal
creation of software within those you
know a niche that's too small today to
support a business just wait five years
right it'll be twice as big right and
then another five years it'll be four
times as big as that so it's hard to
comprehend and I think part of why
people myself included sometimes don't
think about just how big the App Store
is and apple services are is that you
can flight the 95 billion with gross
Billings oh the 95 billion is what all
of Candy Crush plus all the subscription
apps is like gross gross but that 95
billion is Apple's 30 plus all the stuff
that they sell so that's not gross
buildings and in the report you
mentioned the number 1.1 trillion which
is an estimate of the overall gross
buildings of the app store and then
Apple has done reports where they talk
about overall app ecosystem Revenue
where you take into account airbnbs that
are booked through the app that's
published on the App Store rides through
Uber and it's trillions of dollars
flowing through this app economy I mean
it's like a third of the internet right
like the apps are now part of the
internet I don't know if most people
like conceive of it that way or if Apple
conceives of it that way but they've
taken a huge chunk of dinner which is
probably why they're under so much
scrutinies because it's a step back from
the sort of liberal structures of the
internet not to jump from economics into
technology too much but still
fascinating that this far into phones
that the web experience is still not
really seen as the place to do business
on the phone right you would be
surprised and I guess to some degree
Apple wants it that way right the more
they can keep the web experience
substandard to the app experience that's
a better way for them to extract
licensing revenue from their platform
but I don't think it's just Apple I
think also just technologically the web
has not been able to compete from a user
experience perspective with you know we
talk about the apps are getting
regulated look at websites are just
unusable now right like thank you EU
cookie pop-ups right like especially on
mobile the user experience debt that
that adds on mobile is two times as bad
as it is on a website it's the internet
now we're just talking about the
internet I think when we talk about the
App Store in a weird way and the way
we've looked at is the UI ux so much
better within an application versus
within Safari right so even if you're on
Airbnb and you go through it through
your Google search it keeps you under
Safari or Chrome if that's what you're
using any page it still recommends to
open up the app yeah it's where these
companies are investing which is
shocking I mean I don't think companies
would do that unless they were forced
like the technological constraints of
that web platform because there's like a
lot of advantages to shipping on a web
it must be that they can deliver better
especially for the ones like Airbnb
where payments can be done they don't
get the benefit of in-app purchases the
best this is the guy who calls in and
purchases a benefit now uh the benefit
of internet purchases for their service
they have to do direct Commerce with
their customers it's I guess not
surprising but still surprising when you
take a step back it's one of the many
things I think Apple doesn't quite get
enough credit for is that yeah they
could be building out an HTML5 app
platform that is the web but they invest
a ton in making that app experience
really good and they do that not just
because
the web experience doesn't allow them to
charge the 30 or whatever they do it
because it's a native Computing platform
where they can just do more with a
native Computing platform been a Safari
app can do no matter how much they would
invest in that I think that you're
thinking about it exactly right they
love keeping people within the ecosystem
I mean you got to give them credit too
they're one of the ones who really
unlock purchasing through phones they
didn't make it so easy I think the
ecosystem as a whole would be way way
down the fact that you guys completely
trust pushing two buttons or pushing one
button twice on your phone as a complete
secure way to pay is wild if you go back
to like the Singular Wireless days
you're trying to pay with uh yeah I mean
think about that like I mean we're gonna
be the generation that has to manage
that Gap future Generations are gonna be
like yeah I just kind of hold the phone
up and I scan the QR code or double
click something and everything's secure
it happens instantly I don't have to
think about it in two Arenas too they've
done it in app purchases but also the
way you know for most you know Shopify
supports it which is half of Ecom now as
well you get that same experience with
Apple pay which I don't know if we can
measure and account for that but I don't
think it's insignificant they have Apple
pay on on Mac OS I don't I don't know
they do I don't must not have a setup
I'm almost us more willing these days to
do Ecom on my phone even on mobile just
because I get Apple pay I'm probably
twice as likely to convert because it's
like I don't have to pull my credit card
out and type numbers and all that crap
exactly we're talking about this huge
sleeping giant so I think that's why we
wanted to call it out it's one of the
first pages in our report which is just
sometimes people will poo poo like
consumer businesses or the application
area and we're like this is a huge huge
huge Market with lots of dollars so pay
attention and it's growing faster than
almost anything else out there you hit
on just the number of apps do you think
the people looking down their noses are
sort of overlooking this is because of
the fact that there are big winners in
the App Store but there isn't Venture
scale or like big 10 billion dollar IPOs
yet four apps within this do you think
that's part of the reason then it gets
overlooked so two answers one I think
historically or if you're a 40 year old
50 year old venture capitalist private
Equity Firm like the tournament app just
seems like a little Fufu thing right
like something maybe a calculator app or
something to edit photos you don't
understand the economics behind it but
then if you start saying okay well on
your phone Strava billion dollar company
Nike run another outdoor business super
popular Netflix Spotify most people have
them on their phones okay to public
companies Harry single well guess what
you probably use a dating app public
companies billion dollars right so you
start going through this we actually
have a thesis that there will be a lot
more that go public and that'll just
kind of open up people's understanding
of the App Store like what's the hottest
IPO that's gonna happen in 2023
instacart how many of their purchases
come through an app almost all of them
now that's not a consumer subscription
business by any means but it is a mobile
first but it certainly reflects some
sort of consumer Trend right completely
so our argument is that we actually
think of a lot more you kind of talk
about like MyFitnessPal which Francisco
Partners owns another business is doing
millions in profit you could talk about
Onyx which is a hunting business
extremely big business it's close to IPO
scale there's a bunch of them that are
out there and I think you'll see more
and more coming out of Education we have
a bunch of thesis around Family Planning
female Health that eventually there will
be more and more success stories and
then that'll just get people to recycle
their thinking on what it would exist in
this economy and then there's a ton of
what we call SMB level businesses
businesses doing 10 to 20 million in
Revenue which is Big they're doing it
all digitally and they're very
profitable when I think of our user base
which doesn't reflect the greater you
know a lot of those like Titans that you
talked about of consumer subscription
started well before Revenue cat and we
sort of missed as a easy customer we'll
get you someday but we do see I love I
was telling somebody about it recently
these tons of sort of and again maybe
not Venture scale or maybe not IPO scale
not yet and maybe it's not like B2B
where you can scale to a billion dollar
outcome in a matter of single digit
years it might take 15 years in
consumers house land but when you look
at the underlying macro trends that
you're showing it's hard to stand up and
make a straight face argument like it
won't happen right I can't tell you the
timelines might be a little off
expectations but that these won't
produce high margin very stable good
growth businesses I think there's a lot
of evidence that that's going to be the
end State yeah one thing I've been
thinking a lot about lately is just this
increasing willingness to pay and we've
talked about this a little bit in past
episodes with you Eric is just that over
time more and more people are pulling
out the old credit card or their face
when it comes to in-app purchase and
actually paying I think Jacob it was the
last time we talked to Eric that you
mentioned your dad not wanting to pay
for a subscription a NASCAR app for a
NASCAR app
I would guess that at this point or at
some point in the next year he pays for
the NASCAR app yeah there you go yeah
okay so after a conversation I had to
sit him down and be like Dad you know
how I make money
I don't even think it takes that like a
lot of these people who were like oh
apps are free I should never pay for an
app they're running into a NASCAR app
and like okay I'm gonna pay because this
is super valuable to me and so there's
multiple layers of the growth that is
happening in this space is it not only
have iPhones doubled in the last five
years but the number of people who find
something valuable enough to pay via
subscription is growing and there's an
interesting causality thing there is
it's like well are people sentiments
changing or are the incentives there
that are causing companies to find the
product Market fit to expand the market
which I don't think there's really a way
to untangle that right is it natural I
got my dad the subscriber my dad that
made that you know now we're gonna have
to interrogate free will but yeah like
you said both you know when we go back
to this fractal concept of the App Store
growing and these niches getting created
and you'll probably always have our
standard you know Fitness and whatever
these pillars of categories but I don't
see any reason why on some time time
scale most of these niches can't create
meaningful businesses every Niche is
going to produce a unicorn no but enough
are going to create enough of these smbs
for it to be a space like worth entering
for a lot of software creators all this
growth and in-app purchases has brought
the attention of regulators worldwide
and this is something you call out in
the report Eric that there is increasing
pressure on Apple and Google to open up
payments to reduce fees to relax
requirements what's your thinking around
that in 2023 this is always the
literally billion dollar question that
people are asking us and you know I
don't think we have any crystal ball
here in one or if Apple makes a change
you are seeing Google start to make some
shifts the I'll call it pressure from
both the EU and a few other regulatory
both in state and federal here in the US
is starting to increase they kind of won
the lawsuit against epic but listen a
lot of stuff got disclosed and people
are starting to dig into it right now
there's a pretty good lawsuit coming out
of the UK so I believe there's a second
case too with Google and epic as well
that isn't resolves yeah yeah so the
question is like at some point do they
just say hey we're making enough money
here let's rash it back like I think
every app developer can agree that it's
worth something to be able to sell
globally on day one is worth something
and so the question is is that 15 is it
20 I ultimately think at some point
there will be a crack and then that is
just straight cash flow for the app
developer ecosystem and apple will find
a way to make it back because then those
individuals will either lower their
prices to get more people to subscribe
or they generally increase price over
time by adding a lot more features
because they're just so much more
profitable so now they can continue to
invest more and more in their businesses
because they're generating that much
more cash flow so I guarantee there's an
analysis being done at Apple that hey
let's figure this out at some point and
just kind of try to shift some of these
lawsuits off because you just don't want
to be the target of regulators today
Facebook had it Microsoft has had it at
some point that you know I call it the
iso run of the global Regulators will
aim at every major tech company and you
just want to stay under that Limelight
as long as possible so yeah it's a bit
of tactics at this point but I almost
wonder if even a rate cut is going to be
enough it's like once a regulator gets
the b in their Bonnet that they want to
crack down on this I don't think it
becomes because it never really was a
question of Economics right I think it's
a question of power and sort of making
sure that Apple doesn't become bigger
and more powerful than these Fiat
governments like the dma right now is
happening digital markets act in Europe
did you see the ridiculous cyberpunk
press release from the European
Regulators on this oh my God it's so
good it's really good in the show notes
but they like tweeted out who their
Gatekeepers were and for some reason
it's on like a Tron background it's like
technology anyway we're living in a very
strange timeline but I mean they're
already doing it and like apple could
cut rates tomorrow it's over it doesn't
matter like they're gonna fall under
these regulations but it's not over
because if Apple does cut rates to
compete they're gonna win back a lot of
those payments I think part of what
works in your thesis Eric is that if
Apple lowers Ray they're going to pull
back in payments that aren't currently
happening on the App Store like this
weekend I was downloading YouTube TV so
I could watch a football game and then
one of the few quote reader apps that
does let you click a link to go outside
the App Store and I jumped through all
the hurdles and I had to pull out my
credit card to get the three-digit
surgeon general's warning against
outside App Store yeah I had to jump
through all the Hoops but somebody liked
YouTube TV if it were 10 or something in
that ballpark that Apple's charging less
do they want those consumers to be
jumping through all these hoops if there
are alternate app stores in Europe but
developers know that they can make more
money on Apple's app store if Apple
reduces a fee I hope that's an analysis
being done inside Apple too is like how
much of these payments will we win back
if it is 10 12 whatever those numbers I
don't think there's enough McKenzie
consultants in the world to get that
answer right like it's just too
complicated right there's the price
missing pressure in this developer
Behavior then there's consumer Behavior
then there's conversion rates and
throughputs on the App Store stuff I
mean it's like trying to change pricing
at a SAS company not ask me how I know
it's like there's just too many levers
it's like impossible to predict at some
point you just gotta aim and shoot I
don't know I mean it depends on what
side of the demand curve they're on
right like if they cut rates is that
really going to bring people back it's a
lot of effort to like set up those
outside systems so I guess in theory it
all equiliberalizes in the long game but
the thing that's got me a little
Melancholy about it all is it's already
a mess like we've already created a mess
the fact that DNA exists and it will
exist forever it's like another one of
these cookie things maybe we're gonna
get rid of the cookie thing at some
point and the internet will be fixed but
I just worry that this same regulation
without fully understanding the
consequences that has led to the web
being somewhat unusable these days is
going to come to apps and it's
impossible to predict the consequences
but I don't know we'll just have to wait
and see I see like the cat's out of the
bag already that's on Apple right to
take initiative to instead of letting
seven different jurisdictions create
their own laws and then every prep has
to jump through it just take the lead
make a big splash solve the problem and
I think that's my thesis is that they're
smart enough they will make that
decision I think when the trade-off
becomes very apparent if they can solve
it it's already complex again seven
different jurisdictions right and maybe
that was their intent with the first
year 15 they were trying to take off
some of the heat but it's hard to
evaporate 20 billion dollars or whatever
that is like
not free money but it's about as good a
free money yeah it does as close as
you're gonna get right from a regulator
standpoint I do find it really
interesting that I don't think Apple and
Google get enough credit for just how
consumer friendly their payments are you
can go to one place to unsubscribe they
have fraud protection they have all
these kind of layers built in and The
Regulators better regulating Apple and
Google payments directly versus now
anybody oh yeah I don't even think about
it I mean there's laws in the U.S now
that are coming up because you have
people like the New York Times of all
people like making you make a phone call
to cancel your subscription and so there
is from a regulatory standpoint
in that consumer loss yeah yeah net when
it's all done I mean even if the price
cuts and whatever like I mean that's
always been my stance again it's hard to
give up 20 billion dollars in profit
right so maybe Apple overplayed their
hand by not giving some to me it feels
like the market has constructed itself
in such a way that it's oligopolized
right there's only a handful of players
and there's no real way to break that
Monopoly up so now I don't know they're
trying to create some sort of Market
pressure but there's really no way like
you cannot replicate a free market you
know if it's like IE versus Netscape
okay at the end of the day it's an icon
you click on they're sort of like
comparable Alternatives but in-app
purchases and not in-app purchases are
not the same technology right they're
not the same thing but The Regulators
are trying to act as if that's going to
create like sufficiently real Market
pressure again so we've just like half
solved anyway complaining about European
regulations it's my second favorite
activity we can summer it off with it
just stay tuned but it's been like two
years of staying tuned and nobody still
knows what's going on so but I think we
will see like when the dma rolls out
we'll get some hint something will
happen in 2024 yeah for sure one of the
other things you mentioned in the report
that I thought was really interesting
was you proposed a question who will be
the Berkshire Hathaway of app stores so
who will be Eric you pose a question but
give me the answer and maybe for the
finance nerds explain what that means or
the non-finance Nerds yeah if everyone
who has a social life I'll explain this
Berkshire Hathaway is Warren Buffett's
company right and he started up just
cash flowing businesses right if you
look at his portfolio he's got stuff
from like oil and gas pipelines Steve's
Candy which is chocolate candy you know
he used to own textiles Berkshire
Hathaways yeah that was the textile
company right or something exactly that
was the original name right so that was
the founding so basically Buffett his
thesis was like he just buys good
businesses period right it doesn't
matter what industry and so you've seen
Roll-Ups happen in other Industries Car
Wash Industries you've seen them happen
in like doctors clinics where people
kind of get economies of scale and bring
them together and you're starting to see
that in the Apple store but the
interesting thing is we haven't seen it
to the extent we would have expect given
the amount of dollars out of here and
the fragmentation of ownership and if
you think about it the ability to
streamline back-end Services is quite
powerful here once again is a digital
product so you know there's companies
like Maple media and La pending spoons
out of Italy Mosaic which is like an IAC
company in New York they're all doing it
and getting some pretty good scale lots
of profitability but it isn't where we
expect it'll be at three to five years
right so I'm sure you guys have all seen
some Roll-Ups that have happened like
Amazon they raised billions and they did
it within about a span of like six
months absolutely wild now that sector
was probably well oversold and it got
really competitive and then I think a
lot of those businesses are now starting
to Trend backwards they kind of rode the
e-commerce phone so it's probably a bad
example but it's an example of investors
tossing money after a roll of strategy
and we haven't seen that in a considered
subscription space yet and so we've seen
plenty of people do SAS investing we
definitely have some rock stars that do
CSS investing but I think people are
going to wake up to the dollars that are
here and how profitable these businesses
can't be so I listed a couple of the
names that I think have a really big
chance and there's plenty more right
there's reflectively out of Europe
that's coming Union Apex out of Boston
there's a lot of names that are starting
to pick up to come after this sector do
you think part of that is it on the
banking side not being able to price the
risk for debt to buy these things are
there macro because it's like yeah
what's the difference between an app and
a car wash well there's quite a few is
that the reason is it a microeconomic
thing where sellers don't want to sell
or buyers don't want to buy or is it a
macroeconomic thing where it's just like
the current state of interest rates and
compressions and whatnot don't support
it I'd probably breaking into a couple
categories I think debt is a little more
challenging here right their debt has
now started to come for SAS like B2B SAS
software you're seeing private Equity
good pretty decent deadlines to do this
I think you'll be able to see that with
CSS but you need to have a decent scale
three to five million profitability to
get a lender to take a look at it we've
definitely seen some lenders that will
back transactions that we've done are
they getting as favorable leverages as
they would in like a SAS business you
aren't but you also shouldn't take as
much leverage favorable leverage here I
would actually change the definition and
SAS right getting four to five times ass
ebitda isn't
I would recommend getting like two to
three here at consumer so you have a
little more leeway you don't want to get
in trouble on the dead side here that
sounds like just admitting to the
unknowns that CSS is a little bit still
an open question well I won't say
historical question it just has
different characteristics right B2B SAS
you can consistently say you'll have it
was really good B2B SAS right 90 gross
retention people look for much higher
rates and CSS you look at 70 is a really
good first year annual retention rate so
then mathematically you shouldn't take
on that much debt because you don't have
that much cash flow guarantee it's a
math equation but you're much more
exposed to the acquisition environment
which tends to be more volatile yeah and
I think the idea is apps have been
priced all over the board in the last
two or three years there's enough data
points out there now that I think people
will be able to price it much more
accurately and listen my job is to ruin
that pricing by selling my clients for
the highest price it'll be an average
and the average is where people will
look at and try to decide if there's
purchase to be made and so there's a lot
of streamlining you can do on the back
office around marketing content creation
finance and then you can also start
doing bundling so it actually makes
sense to partner a few of these apps
together and you can't do that unless
you truly own it you know there's
companies like palta that's doing some
really cool stuff in health and fitness
they're bundling about the health and
fitness offerings together if you look
at match publicly traded company they
just bundle dating and they don't care
who you are or who you want to date or
who you want to fall in love with
they've got a product for you so you can
cover everything in that space you could
kind of say they're also approach our
halfway updating in the App Store these
days so I do think there'll be a lot
more there'll be stuff that happens in
Fitness and stuff that happens in health
but definitely be stuff that happens in
education check is a really good example
of that when they bought Mathway they'll
definitely do some more stuff on that
front so I say stay tuned to this one we
think there'll be some really big
outcomes here and there have been a lot
of M A in this space any particular ones
you wanted to call out of interesting
deals that have happened recently the
biggest one that I would point to has
been experience just a really big deal
with some Italian Banks they bought out
about 600 million of debt so back to our
debt question Jacob that's a big check
and then we went out and bought Evernote
which is a really famous US app it was a
good business had kind of made me been
left by the wayside but rumor has it
they bought that won't disclose anything
but well north of 100 million dollars
it's a big business to buy so I think
that's one I think there'll be a few
more that start coming out if you look
at what Francisco Partners just did with
the Weather Channel people don't
understand that but there's a paid
subscription feature in The Weather
Channel That's wildly profitable and
Francisco Partners did the same thing
with MyFitnessPal which is once again
wildly profitable and it's a free app so
I think you just need more people to
start to think through that right and
understand the economics and then the
cash flows and I think you'll see some
more and more big outcomes here you said
a lot of people don't understand it I
don't understand it so IBM bought the
Weather Channel it was like a subsidiary
of IBM and then that just got spun out
of IBM to a private Equity like why and
do you know any more about why and how
all that happened their goal right if
they used to take the Weather Channel
and take it from being you know Legacy
brand that was on TV 24 7 and a lot of
households move it off cable and turn it
into you know if you look at Apple
weather it's okay I don't think anyone's
Blown Away by it a lot of people using a
third-party weather app but it is
something that you look at every single
day and so there's a lot of ways to
monetize an app or service that you use
every day it's a good example of like
dipping their toe kind of starting to
understand this and maybe they're like
okay now we can see some replicability
here I'm gonna be interesting to know
what their exit strategies are for those
right because I don't think they're
going to hold them indefinitely I don't
know there's buyers for everything I
guess the question would be do they
think of it as an IPO or do they think
of it as flipped to one of these holding
companies potentially right or they
don't exist yet do their own roll-up and
IPO a bundle between Weather Channel
MyFitnessPal a couple other big
businesses spins out us its own IPO
should be like another ISE yeah I think
all the above is on their board well one
of the things I think the Weather
Channel Evernote and others all have in
common too is this push into B2B from B
to C apps Weather Channel and maybe this
is part of what Francisco Partners is
headed toward is that the B2B weather
data space is huge and there's so many
examples notion going from more B to B
to more B to C there's like just this
real blending of the use cases between
B2B and B to C these days and you
highlight that in this report what are
some of the interesting things you're
seeing in that blending of B2B and b2c
so coming out from the b2c side right a
lot of businesses ramped up during
Covenant on b2c people were needing new
solutions to new problems they never had
before Peloton is a great example
headspace calm all it did very well
because people were stressed they didn't
go to church right there looking for
something different they didn't go see
their therapist so those companies took
off now I think some of the errors come
out of their sales and so people are
looking for new avenues of growth and
B2B is a huge untapped market and if you
sit back and say okay does everything a
consumer Need Is that real readily
applicable for business answers no of
course not but there are definitely a
few that make a ton of sense for
businesses to offer their employees as
either benefits or ways to make them
more productive or to make their
Workforce more efficient so slack right
if you think about it that way it
started as b2c they're just selling to
small individuals they could create
teams and then they start selling to
p2bs and Enterprises Dropbox exact same
solution right they started offering
like file sharing to one person and then
organizations were like hey I could just
use this to replace what I'm using on a
server let me just go with that and so
the thesis we've had and we've seen this
played out with companies like fin on
headspace and then merger Ginger is that
if you're designing a product that
consumers love not just love because
they have to use it like your healthcare
app but love it because like hey I will
pay money for it it's that good it's
that efficient it makes my life that
much better there's probably a strong
rationale that businesses will want to
use this and so you've seen this happen
in like an education right like
lynda.com they sold a LinkedIn and
they're selling courses to individuals
and now they take LinkedIn Salesforce
with selling recruiting services and
they sell them in courses to businesses
help your employees get better help your
employees get smarter right it's the
same use case you're just using a
different sales force so what we think
is the magic that Builders have around
designing It Best in Class service for
consumers something once in the
individual you make takeable pay for you
can sell that to B2B pretty easily if
there's a strong benefit you can show to
either Workforce or their productivity
and so it's a really nice growth Avenue
for a lot of companies if it makes the
right fit so we're seeing a lot of
companies do that I wouldn't call it a
pivot I would call it a growth extension
yeah it's a new channel which follows
the trends of consumerification of SAS
in the workplace as well right bring
your own device all those buzzwords of
five years ago or six years ago I always
like to shout out photo room one of our
customers and friend of mine's app
because I would call them B2B in a lot
of ways because they sell to like
Shopify sellers it's purchased on the
App Store but you know I think so much
about their success has been the
stickiness of selling to somebody who's
using their app for a business use case
even if it's in this sort of prosumer
Independent Business Runner persona but
then you've also seen them pivot to
opening up their tooling and selling an
API now right which they are selling in
a fully B2B motion which is I guess
talking about going that route of
understanding who else you can sell this
technology it's all useful technology
right it's just bundling in channels
Evan canvas another really a good
example right we started off making
software for yearbooks right for schools
yeah right about as smbs you can get it
selling into the Australian school
market and then individuals use it bands
use it wedding planners use it so all of
a sudden that growler spans and then all
of a sudden it's competing Head To Toe
with Adobe that's really fascinating to
me that you managed to move that quickly
but it's because the app is so well
designed for a consumer that it just
takes off and a B2B use case is
relatively apparent yeah it's easy to
sell when people want your software and
I wonder if some of this B2B b2c play
won't even fully cannibalize each other
like I was actually just thinking the
other day I use YouTube for work now
Jacob my boss's boss Jacob we can have
the conversation Here YouTube premium
well I don't so I was actually just
thinking the other day we should get it
on the revenue account I open it
sometimes and I get real annoyed so
right exactly open my personal YouTube
account which I have premium all right
it's officially approved we can get
premium for the company YouTube account
but this is a perfect example and it's
not cannibalization because I'm not
going to log into my Revenue cat email
on my TV to get YouTube ad free or
whatever but it's really annoying and
I'm not going to log into my personal
Gmail online
browser window that's my personal stuff
on my work computer which you're not
supposed to do until oit we don't have
an I.T department but yeah it's
interesting though it's like massively
underpriced if you think about that so
we'll pay 9.99 a month for our whole
company to have YouTube premium and like
when really the value we derive out of
consuming content from YouTube but then
also creating content on YouTube and all
that stuff is much much higher than that
that's always the hard part it's like
sometimes you're selling something to do
with consumer and to a business and like
even on a per seat basis you need to
charge 10x in the business context for
exactly the same thing that's hard like
we experience it at Revenue cat like
some of our long tail looks very much
like consumers they're like small Indies
and then we're also trying to sell the
same product for like a much higher
price point I think the other end of the
market and it does take a little bit of
value capture arguments and sort of
making sure we tell the story in the
right way so it's not easy on the
pricing side at least yeah totally agree
but I think you'll see it happen more
and more another thing you mentioned is
the three C's content Commerce and
community and this is one of the big
focuses of the report this year tell me
about that yeah so it's a thesis we've
been kicking around we call it the three
C's but it's as you exactly called out
it's content Commerce community and so
the way we've thought about this is any
category right regardless of what type
of Industry you're in if you're a
consumer brand the hardest things you
have is acquiring new customers getting
them to do a purchase and then keeping
them up like their LTV that applies to
everything from like selling Coke or
Pepsi to selling a consumer subscription
app and so if you looked at like a lot
of the d2c brands that have taken off in
Luggage in female health and nutrition
in almost any category right their
biggest challenge is finding users and
so what we've seen happen and we've done
this in a few deals I won't name which
ones but if you create really high
quality content right that's SEO
searchable or eventually will be AI
searchable the consumer will find you
but you have to produce that Best in
Class content that provides a solution
to whatever question they're typing into
that browser which is like how do I lose
weight how do I need a friend how do I
find someone to date right all these
questions that consumers ask every day
if you provide top level answers to that
consumers will find you one way shape or
form so that's the content and then you
have to convince them to do a purchase
and then that purchase can take a
variety of features and that could be
any conference purchase or maybe try
order of vitamins or maybe you do a
trial right which is hey I'm subscribing
to an app but I'm not really in there
yet I just want to test it but it's
getting someone to finally trust you
with a purchase and then ultimately
sometimes those are one-time purchases
and you don't fall in love with the
product but like the most passionate
ones will want something more with you
want to engage with you that want to
feel part of the brand and that's the
community and what we've seen is people
that monetize those communities with
subscriptions and then the whole thing
is kind of wrapped up by user generated
content and that flows right up into the
top of the funnel which is you know
acquiring the users and so we've seen
companies start to do this like mediator
which is a TCG portfolio company you'll
see a lot of others where the passion
that people have for certain brands goes
them Beyond like just a purchase history
right they wear t-shirts of the company
and you think about that and that's just
a weird way to be a walking billboard
for certain companies but I see tons of
people with Discord t-shirts and it's
just part of their Persona they like to
be part of that they like to be part of
that group and so what we've seen is
we're helping a couple of companies now
like you should have all three of those
stacks and if you don't you might want
to look at buying one of them right and
then you can really expand the LTB of
your user or you can make it much easier
to acquire a customer for free right so
your marketing budgets go way way down
that's an area we're spending a lot of
time focusing on that's our thesis
that's fascinating and with all these
things like that's not going to work for
every business different businesses are
going to have to find different ways to
solve that top of funnel we actually
talked about this on the most recent
podcast with Reed deramus he was at
Crunchyroll and at Crunchyroll they had
that t-shirt task so it's funny you
brought up the t-shirt is that you're
going to have apps that people aren't
going to wear your T-shirt and that's
okay but the magic of those three
together is part of what's going to
build these massive massive companies
and I think you're right that Community
piece I think is overlooked in kind of
the app space it's like are you just
another app or are you something people
really deeply care about and then how do
you position yourself more in that
direction it maps to like the three
challenges I think of when we're
thinking about like product strategy for
Revenue cat and stuff like that that all
apps have it's acquisition conversion
and retention right so it's like content
for acquisition Commerce and conversion
same thing and then and Community is a
huge lever for retention right like
continual creation of content or like
user generated content and Affinity
content can be a very broad definition
right like something has to entice
somebody to try your app out right even
just your your app store Pages content
right like that's a form of Storytelling
and discovery that you need to nail it's
probably not sufficient to lead to some
of the like margins that you've been
talking about Eric today you need to
have like a lower cost channel of
acquisition than that there's no
consumer subscription business that
doesn't have to solve acquisition
conversion and retention like that's it
those are the three problems in a
Perfect Analogy rate so I just had a
daughter well I didn't have one my wife
had one I was around for that I now have
a daughter I was kind of digging to this
space and we talked about this report
like we think of big unicorns and female
health and a perfect example if you
think about just the I know you guys
have kids but for similar listeners that
don't right if you're thinking about
getting pregnant there's a ton of apps
and solutions you have for women that
can think about it right and they'll
find those and there's free and there's
paid but that is like the start of that
journey and that Journey ends hopefully
with pregnancy right and there's a bunch
of stuff you could buy once you're
either pregnant or just had the baby
everything from Medical Services to
vitamins to cameras to different tools
for measurement tons of stuff like it's
literally an unlimited e-commerce
offering I noticed my spend went up when
I entered that phase in my life a little
bit Yeah
unexplained hits over the last 13 months
and I've got four so multiply all those
by four I think you can play as much as
David all right David you're not all
prefer as cool as you I'm just at one
give me a break but anyway and then you
have the the baby right and then there's
tons of baby toys you can buy I want
each one of those value chains right if
you're in the female Health space you
can acquire the customers with content
and a nice service but then you lose
them once they have the baby there's a
natural sharing point and then if you're
selling baby Goods you're competing with
everyone on Amazon on Google for key
Search terms like baby blanket for baby
monitor for baby clothes right that is a
crazy competitor category and then
ultimately you lose that customer at
some point and so like if you put those
three categories together like
pre-pregnancy pregnancy pregnancy and
baby that LTV that consumer goes from
one purchase to effectively like three
years that's a huge shift in LTV and if
you can acquire those customers at the
very beginning at that point and then
monetize them across that entire next 36
months it changes the entire CAC of
those businesses so it's a big thesis
for people how and we're actively having
conversations about it so there is a
solution there and the question I ask
myself on female Health but like who's
the apple of female health I was the
brand you go to that is by far the best
and you don't question it you just buy
it and there isn't one there should be
one right for something that happens
millions of times a year why isn't there
an Apple female Health yeah well and
fintech is one of the six opportunities
you highlight in the report as quote
category Killers is categories where you
see the potential to build massive
businesses to become the apple of
fintech to become the apple of act so
talk me through the other category
killer potentials so category killer our
thesis is in consumer subscription right
it generally ends up being like a
duopoly of two to four major players in
each category and then a bunch of
smaller businesses that are still good
but won't hit like unicorn billion
dollar exits right you see this in
dating you see this in Fitness you see
this in entertainment right both at
video and music there's only a few
winners Duolingo and Babel great yeah
perfect example on education they're
checking there with busu which is a
cheap people have deal hashtag
advertising so then we kind of looked at
what are the categories that don't have
those natural winners right where are
the names that you don't see the
automatic answer for when you're looking
to do something and so like femtech was
one we think Family Management is a huge
category everyone uses outlook for their
personal life but like what's the
product for the chief household officer
who's in charge of scheduling activities
people are trying to act together like
calendly and merging a couple calendars
and then doing some budgeting tools I've
seen some d2c Hardware stuff for this
but but I'm also I see that stuff and
I'm like that's not the problem it's
putting on the wall is not the problem
this is a data merger issue right I go
through this constantly my wife's been
out of town a lot and our shared
calendars are a disaster and she
actually bought a physical calendar like
oh I'm gonna do it it's easy this year
and then she has to be out of town and
like now I have to run all the playbooks
and it's not on my calendar we're on the
physical calendar that we just got a
piece of paper that we put on the fridge
and we write dates down on it which
again when you travel is bad I got
embarrassed where I was like I had to
call the doctor for my daughter I have
no idea who my daughter's doctor was not
a clue like I couldn't find it right my
wife knew her on a first name basis we
knew each other well I had no idea right
that should easily be able for me to
find up there and all that information
could easily be sync we have it all it
sits somewhere within this yeah I mean
we've solved this problem in in the
Enterprise if you will right and there
are players already in this space like
what do you think it's going to take for
one of these to break out man I've
looked at them and it's like I've tried
and it's hard to use or or whatever like
what's it going to take I think it's
going to be the API intersection right
you got to have someone come in with a
bunch of money and start spending money
on paying people to get their data API
is connecting from like mint.com you got
to be able to access calendar dates
school dates but a lot of that you can
start to solve that with AI right if
you're able to read emails and you say
all right any email I'll get from St
Andrews preschool that immediately goes
into our family calendar as an activity
if you start saying hey my personal AI
that sits on my phone read the text
messages that come in and mention
Jimmy's soccer practice pull that in so
I think not to spin off in an AI but
it's just data and it's structuring that
data into an output or a dashboard I
don't think it's that challenging at the
end of the day it makes me think of
flighty our friend Ryan Jones and his
app which is not an app that hadn't been
tackled before but like sometimes these
categories I feel like they just need a
bit of an otor approach right like
somebody who's going to come in and
really build you know I think about this
calendar app I use on desktop called
KRON that got bought by notion I think
in these basic apps there's still
opportunities for really Discerning and
caring user experience people to come in
and that's my feeling with David like
you didn't use it because the product
Market if it wasn't there the user
experience wasn't there like if they had
designed the user experience right and
designing the user experience right for
product Market fit means making that
onboarding so sticky that you wouldn't
have got frustrated and confused and
like it would have just been easy to use
right it requires a lot of setup it may
even have to have required like a
service angle right to onboard yeah you
can buy some Mackenzie Consultants to
come in and set up a hired Accenture to
do my family calendar
sleeper to win the Family Management I
recently ramped up with green light and
it was a huge onboarding and everything
else but now my kids all have credit
cards we can give them allowance right
to their credit card it's actually a
phenomenal service and back to some of
the topics in the report we originally
used green light like five years ago and
it just wasn't there yet it was a lot of
hassles my kids were young and then
recently is sitting at the pool with
said fellow dad the dad was like oh yeah
my kids are doing all these chores I'm
like what are you how are you doing that
oh yeah we got this green light card and
we put bounties you know on the chores
and then they go do them and they get
paid and it's this great one layer of
Family Management then I went and signed
back up like five years later I've been
reacquired it takes that long it takes
that long to build really great software
right five years to make a really great
app there are plenty of examples out
there of apps that really it just takes
a long time to like iterate and back to
investment Eric the amount of money you
need to like front load that kind of
development time maybe isn't always that
easy but honestly you can get an app to
profitability I mean slopes may be a
good example of an app that has been
around for a long time and certainly
wasn't as functional and featureful when
it started to where it is today it's a
Powerhouse today it wasn't like that on
versions one and two I mean you need the
ability to structure the data and then
it's going to be some sort of a modular
thing where like you pull in the school
functionality right you maybe pay a
little bit more to upgrade to that and
then you pull in the college planning or
the financial tour the chores tool maybe
pull in the grocery purchase right every
kid can select something for the grocery
sure that's a huge Cairo right I think
in the word of mouth of that category
will be massive we think Sports is
another big one and this kind of ties
into Family Management but it's very
separate which is like David if you ask
yourself how much do you spend on Youth
Sports a year between like fees
registration driving uniforms gear I'm
guessing it's starting to approach like
five figures I don't know David's kids
just do open AI that's what his big
bills are I mean put Roblox into that
right whatever my calls yeah my
daughter's playing volleyball in the
house I feel you it's not five figures
yet but we're trying to get my two
youngest into soccer so we're headed
that direction and you're right I mean
driving them all around for games and
then I was actually just talking to a
colleague about the apps in this space
and just how challenging they are to use
and their full screen ads and like it's
just not a great space right now but
huge opportunity like you said there's
ton of spending a ton of coordination
there's a lot going on in that
opportunity right where there's an
opportunity somebody will create the
Uber app that will Christine or
something like that called 12.00 month
easy math right and it just streamlines
everything look at class dojo they did
for in the classroom right it wasn't
through like some funny sales Channel
Through schools they went around it with
the b2c motion you can probably
replicate that in a lot of these
categories yeah so I think that's
another one and then the last one I'll
mention is private wealth and Tax
Advisor right and I think a lot of this
not to hardware and open AI or AI tools
but a lot of this data is out there your
tax code is very publicly written every
day it's just impossible to read and
it's impossible to customize it to you
how does this apply to me in my
situation and so like if you look at
like what intuit's doing and there's a
bunch of other products that are coming
up to kind of solve like what's the
level between like wealthfront and like
Morgan Stan the Goldman Sachs people
with like 50 that's called 100 000 in
assets to a million right that's a huge
chunk of America and they all deserve
something that's customized and probably
Tech enabled and makes their life super
simple and removes a lot of their
complaints and the concerns and the
friction and just provides you
suggestions on what you should do to
manage your money it's sitting in your
checking account you should move over to
the savings account takes nothing and it
gives you five percent first that is a
really valuable tool that I think what
people are going to build for and you
mentioned Ai and into its play into
using more of AI to enhance their tools
it creates an interesting shift in how
these tools can be monetized because
Apple's been pretty clear that if it's
software driven and high margin like an
AI helper would be that's got to go
through IAP and I don't think Apple's
gonna seed that ground because I think
that's going to be a huge you know if
you think of the marginal growth in the
App Store in the next five years it's
going to come from these AI tools your
previous wealth manager app might have
circumvented App Store policies or App
Store payments because it could have
gone through you're paying an actual
human being now if it's AI sorry Apple's
going to get their Vig on that for sure
yeah but you could probably easily do it
as a subscription right and then they
just make suggestions and then you log
into your app and make the changes or
there's ways to make connections so it
actually doesn't flow through the app
right right right right right right
right couldn't log into my Chase account
do something for me right move it around
some of these fintechs get around that
that's one way to get around IAP though
is like to have account management which
I honestly think at some point Apple's
gonna look at because there's some of
these companies providing purely
software services but because they have
an attached bank account they're just
Drafting and it's like that's not gonna
last forever Apple's gonna start
cracking down good question it's got to
get their money yeah well hey I wanted
to wrap up on a really fascinating stat
and that's the fact that nearly 80
percent of companies featured in the
annual CSS report that you've done have
either raised or sold and had a great
exit any special picks this year that
you're highlighting I've got a lot of
picks I mean the status and this is a
little bit of a humble brag but every
year in our report starting in 2019 we
profile three Builders right three
companies that are building stuff that
are doing some cool things I think we've
been really good at picking so we
profiled all Trails which raised a big
round from Primera blinkist which sold
to go one Prodigy Math you know I think
we profiled Revenue cat back in the day
I don't know if you guys remember that
play on got sold to KTR and a huge deal
close to 800 million there's a bunch of
success stories there this year I think
every one of our picks is great right
we've got open snow which is doing
something in the weather space we have
spot gamma which is in the financial
newsletter space with a huge sleeping
genome I think that's a big space
talking parents who I think David was on
your podcast this is a family management
business right for divorced parents who
have a very specific yeah it's like a
certain niche of that category right 50
of marriage is then in divorce which is
awful but even if you go to 10 it's a
huge huge damn
lemonade out of lemons over here
tell you I hope it goes to zero but all
those are real strong winners I love
open snow by the way I'm glad you
mentioned I've been on and off when I
lived in California as a subscriber it
was like the best snow prediction every
year like they hire three people to
produce content you're like that's a
totally like meteorologists on staff
like talking and stuff I've always
thought they were like using the
fraction of your epics keep pass right
you save money everything yeah yeah yeah
all right Eric well it was so fun
chatting we're gonna share a link to the
report which will be out before this
podcast airs so you'll be able to go
right to the show notes and download the
report anything else you want to share
Eric as we're wrapping up we love
getting inbounds from your guest David
so if anyone has anything to ask like
reach out eric.crowley gpeoplehound.com
or active on LinkedIn and Twitter and
then our report's free so jump on the
website when it's published download it
tell us where we get wrong right I don't
care if I got something right you know
tell me what I got wrong come out
challenge our assumptions so we'd love
to hear from everyone yeah you guys help
people sell app businesses right like
that's the short of it right if you've
got an app Business and you're
interested in knowing longer owning that
app business for in exchange for a pile
of money maybe talk to Eric we brought
into subscription businesses right we
that's that's our specialty if you're
selling to Consumers and you're selling
a subscription we think we are one of
One Bank you should call if anybody
who's a Founder who goes to try to get a
loan for a mortgage don't talk to a bank
that doesn't understand your situation
because it ends poorly we speak your
language we'll be able to log into your
Revenue cat dashboard and tell you
everything that's going on and just so
our listeners are aware you've told me I
think the figure is somewhere around
like a 10 million dollar exit is where
it starts to make sense to engage G
people Hound so we're not talking so
you're out for 100 000 and call Eric you
gotta have a fairly the transactions get
that big you want Partners like you
don't want to do this yourself because
if little mistakes start to be six
figure differences right so we are not
cheap and I'm very proud of that paper
quality but I think and we'll be
transparent with everyone like hey don't
use a banker or use a banker but not us
we're always happy to give free guidance
too it's part of what we give back to
the ecosystem awesome thanks so much
Eric it's great chatting with you today
it's always a pleasure to be on I really
appreciate it
[Music]
thanks so much for listening
if you have a minute please leave a
review in your favorite podcast player
you can also stop by
chat.subclub.com to join our private
community
foreign
[Music]